Colm?
Colm ?
Are you coming out to the pub, Colm?
Viens-tu au pub ?
It's 2:00, like.
Il est 14 h.
Will I see you down there, so?
On se verra là-bas, alors ?
I'll see you down there, so.
On se verra là-bas.
What are you doin' home?
Que fais-tu à la maison ?
Brother?
Frérot ?
I knocked on ColmSonnyLarry. He's just sitting there.
J'ai cogné chez ColmSonnyLarry. Il était assis là.
Sitting there doin' what?
Assis à faire quoi ?
Sittin' there doin' nothing.
Assis sans rien faire.
Smoking.
Il fumait.
Was he asleep?
Dormait-il ?
He was smoking, Siobhan.
Il fumait, Siobhán. On ne fume pas en dormant.
Have ye been rowing?
Vous êtes-vous chicanés ?
We haven't been rowin'.
Non.
I don't think we've been rowin'.
Enfin, je ne crois pas.
Have we been rowin'?
S'est-on chicanés ?
Why wouldn't he answer the door to me?
Pourquoi ne m'a-t-il pas ouvert ?
Maybe he just doesn't like you no more.
Peut-être qu'il en a assez de toi.
Pint, Jonjo.
Une bière, Jonjo.
Is Colm not with you?
Colm n'est pas avec toi ?
No.Colm's always with you.
- Non. - Il est toujours avec toi.
I know.Did you not knock for him?
- Je sais. - As-tu cogné chez lui ?
I did knock for him.
Oui.
Well, where is he? Just sittin' there.
- Où est-il ? - Assis là.
Sittin' there doin' what?
Assis à faire quoi ?
Sittin' there doing nothin'.
Assis sans rien faire.
Smokin'.
Il fume.
Have ye been rowin'?
Vous êtes-vous chicanés ?
I don't think we've been rowin'.
Je ne crois pas.
Sounds like ye've been rowin'.
On dirait que oui.
It does sound like we've been rowin'.
C'est vrai, on dirait que oui.
Will I try him again?
Devrais-je y retourner ?
That'd be the best thing.
C'est la chose à faire.
Officer Kearney.
Agent Kearney.
Never says "hello."
Il ne dit jamais bonjour.
Never fecking says "hello."
Jamais un maudit bonjour.
Colm?
Colm ?
The door was open, Colm.
C'était ouvert.
Where the hell are you headin' off to?
Où vas-tu comme ça ?
Everybody?JONJO: No, this is true.
- Tout le monde ? - C'est vrai.
He scored six points from open play.
Il a marqué six fois, jeu ouvert.
He was barely the size of a dwarf!
Il était petit comme un nain !
This is true!
C'est la vérité !
Howdo. MAN: Howdo, Padraic.
- Bonjour. - Bonjour, Pádraic.
Sit somewhere else.
Assieds-toi ailleurs.
Huh?
Hein ?
He has his pint there, Colm,
Sa bière est là,
from when he came in and ordered his pint from before.
celle qu'il a commandée plus tôt.
Okay.
D'accord.
I'll sit somewhere else, so.
Je m'assoirai ailleurs, alors.
Are ye rowin'?
Vous êtes-vous chicanés ?
I didn't think we were rowin'.
Je ne le croyais pas.
Well, ye are rowin'.
Vous êtes en chicane.
He's sittin' outside
Mais oui. Il est dehors
on his own like a whatchamacallit.
tout seul comme un trucmuche.
It does look like we're rowin'.
On dirait qu'on est en chicane.
Well, I suppose I'd best go talk to him, so.
Je devrais lui parler, alors.
See what all this is fecking about.
Voir de quoi il est question.
That'd be the best thing.
C'est la chose à faire.
Now I'm sittin' here next to you,
Je m'assieds avec toi.
and if you're goin' back inside, I'm followin' you inside,
Si tu entres, je te suivrai.
and if you're goin' home, I'm followin' you there, too.
Si tu retournes chez toi, je te suivrai aussi.
Now, if I've done somethin' to ya,
Si je t'ai fait quelque chose,
just tell me what I've done to ya.
dis-moi simplement quoi.
And if I've said somethin' to ya,
Si je t'ai insulté...
But if I did, then tell me what it was,
Mais si c'est le cas, dis-le-moi,
and I'll say sorry for that too, Colm.
et je m'excuserai pour ça, Colm.
Just stop running away from me like some fool of a moody schoolchild.
Mais arrête de me tourner le dos comme un enfant qui boude.
But you didn't say anything to me.
Tu ne m'as pas insulté.
And you didn't do anything to me.
Et tu ne m'as rien fait.
That's what I was thinking, like.
C'est bien ce que je pensais.
I just don't like you no more.
J'en ai assez de toi, c'est tout.
You do like me.
Mais tu m'aimes bien.
I don't.
Non.
But you liked me yesterday.
Tu m'aimais bien hier.
Oh, did I, yeah?
Vraiment ?
I thought you did.
Je le croyais.
Padraic.
Pádraic.
Dominic.
Dominic.
What's the matter with ya?
Qu'est-ce que tu as ?
There's nothing the matter with me, for God's sake.
Je n'ai rien, pour l'amour.
Look at this I found.
Regarde ce que j'ai trouvé.
A stick with a hook.
Un bâton avec un crochet.
What would you use it for, I wonder?
À quoi ça peut servir ?
To hook things that were the length of a stick away?
À accrocher des choses à distance d'un bâton ?
Where you goin'?
Où vas-tu ?
Down here.
Par là.
As good a plan as any!
Bonne idée !
Have you any fags?No.
- As-tu des cigarettes ? - Non.
Uh, you do. You always have fags.
Tu en as toujours.
ColmSonnyLarry's at Jonjo's handing out a rake of fags.
ColmSonnyLarry en distribue chez Jonjo.
Whoever's in the mood for one.
Il en donne à qui en veut.
Is he?No!
- Pour vrai ? - Non !
You're behavin' awful unusual.
Tu agis étrangement.
What are you doin' here?
Que fais-tu ici ?
Was the pub closed?
Le pub est fermé ?
No, it was open.
Non, il est ouvert.
Anything in the paper?
Des nouvelles intéressantes ?
Just the Civil War still.Ugh.
La guerre civile continue.
A bad do.
C'est terrible.
Mrs. McCormick's comin' over later, Padraic. I couldn't avoid her.
Mme McCormick viendra plus tard. Je n'ai pas pu l'éviter.
I don't know if you're gonna be in or out, but you're usually out.
J'ignore si tu seras sorti. En général, tu sors.
Am I?
Ah bon ?
You are. Yeah, you know you are.
Tu sais bien que oui.
I don't care, Siobhan.
Je m'en fiche, Siobhán.
This is your house, too.
C'est aussi ta maison.
Is it six years since your mammy and daddy died, Siobhan,
Y a-t-il six ans que tes parents sont morts, Siobhán,
or is it seven years since they died?
ou sept ans ?
It's coming up to eight years, Mrs. McCormick, aye.
Ça fera bientôt huit ans, Mme McCormick.
Is it comin' up to eight years?
Ça fera bientôt huit ans ?
Doesn't time be flyin'?
Le temps passe vite, hein ?
Aye, when you're havin' fun.
Oui, quand on s'amuse.
Oh, be off to the pub now, Padraic,
Va au pub au lieu de nous embêter.
I don't have to be down there every night, do I?
Je ne suis pas obligé d'y aller chaque soir.
ColmSonnyLarry's scared him off, I suppose.
ColmSonnyLarry lui a fait peur, j'imagine.
What did you hear of ColmSonnyLarry?
Qu'avez-vous entendu à propos de lui ?
Didn't you and he used to be the best of friends?
Vous étiez meilleurs amis, non ?
We're still the best of friends.
On l'est toujours.
No, you're not. Who says we're not?
- Non. - Qui vous a dit ça ?
She says.
Elle.
Ah, for God's sake, Siobhan.
Pour l'amour, Siobhán.
I said nothing of the like, Mrs. McCormick! I was just chatting.
Je n'ai rien dit de la sorte ! On bavardait, c'est tout.
Now, you go off to Jonjo's, Padraic,
Va chez Jonjo, Pádraic, tu nous déranges.
She never gets a chance 'cause you avoid her.
Parce que tu l'évites.
I do not avoid her!
Pas du tout !
You hide behind walls if she's coming up the road.
Tu te caches derrière un mur si tu la vois approcher.
I do not!
Je ne me cache pas
h... hide behind walls.
derrière un mur.
Good luck to ye.
Bonne chance à vous.
Whatever it is you're fightin' about.
Peu importe ce pour quoi vous luttez.
I didn't hear there was to be a session.
J'ignorais qu'il y aurait de la musique.
Last-minute thing.
C'était spontané.
Colm decided.
Une idée de Colm.
All the ladies love Colm, you know. Always did.
Les femmes l'adorent, tu sais. Depuis toujours.
Yeah? That's not true.
Ah bon ? C'est faux.
You're still barred, Dominic! Out!
Je t'ai banni, Dominic ! Dehors !
You said barred until April.
Tu m'as banni jusqu'en avril.
What are we now?
On est quel mois ?
April.
Avril.
Well, put that stick outside anyways,
Laisse ce bâton dehors et n'embête pas les femmes.
There's women?
Il y a des femmes ?
There is women.
Il y a des femmes.
And good ones.
De belles femmes.
If we sat next to Colm, the women would have to talk to us too,
Si on s'assoit avec Colm, les femmes seront obligées
and then we could get at them with our small talk.
de bavarder avec nous aussi.
I'm happy enough sittin' here, now.
Je suis bien ici.
Are ya, yeah?
Vraiment ?
Are ya happy enough, yeah?
Es-tu bien ici ?
I can't stand the maudlin' ones.
Je n'aime pas ces chants geignards.
Play somethin' dancey, Colm!
Joue quelque chose d'enjoué, Colm !
To dance to.
Pour qu'on danse.
And not have that mope whining.
Ça suffit, ce pleurnichage.
Here, amn't I in enough trouble with him without your mouthing?
J'ai assez d'ennuis avec lui sans ta grande gueule.
What trouble in are you in with him?
Quel genre d'ennuis ?
doesn't want to be friends with me no more.
plus envie qu'on soit amis.
What is he, 12?
Il a 12 ans ou quoi ?
Why does he not want to be friends with you no more?
Pourquoi ne veut-il plus être ton ami ?
Daddy'll kill us if we wake him when he's been wanking.
Papa nous tuera si on le réveille après qu'il s'est branlé.
You won't get into trouble for taking his poteen?
Tu n'auras pas d'ennuis pour avoir pris sa bouteille ?
I will get into trouble,
J'aurai des ennuis,
but fuck it.
mais au diable tout ça.
I saw cannon-fire and rifle-fire on the mainland tonight.
Il y avait des tirs de canons et de fusils sur la grande île.
Did you see it?
As-tu vu ?
That'll be the Civil War.
C'est la guerre civile.
I know that, sure.
Je sais.
Me, I pay no attention to wars. I'm agin 'em.
Je ne m'occupe pas des guerres. Je suis contre.
Wars and soap.
Les guerres et le savon.
I tell you this much.
Je vais te dire une chose.
We're good at chatting, aren't we?
On bavarde bien ensemble, non ?
Me and you?
Toi et moi ?
Your sister, does she like to chat?
Ta sœur aime-t-elle bavarder ?
Not as much as most women, but she'll chat, like.
Pas autant que les autres femmes, mais oui.
She more likes reading.
Elle préfère lire.
Reading?
Lire ?
Feckin' hell.
Bon Dieu.
Reading.
Lire.
And did you ever see her with no clothes on?
L'as-tu déjà vue toute nue ?
I didn't.
Non.
Did you not, and you her brother?
Même en étant son frère ?
Not even as a child?
Quand vous étiez petits ?
What types of things?
Quelles choses ?
Sisters with no clothes on!
Les sœurs toutes nues !
You saw my daddy with no clothes on.
Tu as vu mon père tout nu.
And till the day I die, I'll wish I hadn't.
Et je le regretterai jusqu'à ma mort.
Sure, don't I know it.
Je te comprends.
The tiny, brown cock on him.
Lui et sa minuscule bite brune.
What's the matter with him?
Qu'est-ce qu'il a ?
Maybe bad news he's had?
Il a peut-être reçu de mauvaises nouvelles ?
Daddy?
Mon père ?
No, ColmSonnyLarry.
Non, ColmSonnyLarry.
Didn't I tell ya I'd be off if you went
Je t'ai dit que je partirais si tu t'en plaignais encore.
I tell ya, it didn't look like he had bad news tonight.
Il n'avait pas l'air d'avoir eu de mauvaises nouvelles.
It looked like a weight was lifted from his shoulders tonight.
Il semblait plutôt libéré d'un fardeau.
Just bringing me cows past.
Je mène mes vaches.
What?
Quoi ?
I was just bringing me cows past.
Je n'essayais pas de...
You don't usually bring them this way.
Tu ne les mènes jamais par ici.
I don't, but then the little fella
Non, mais comme le veau a eu peur d'une poule au coin...
I only...
Je viens...
I only just saw what month we changed to yesterday.
Je viens de comprendre quel jour c'était hier.
More fool me?
As-tu d'autres poissons ?
Changed to April.
C'était le 1er avril.
So, will I be callin' for ya on me way to the pub later?
Devrais-je passer chez toi en allant au pub ?
I will so.
Je passerai.
Anyways,
Bon...
I better chase after these goons
Je vais rattraper mes bêtes qui se sauvent.
Maybe they don't like me no more neither.
Elles en ont peut-être assez de moi aussi.
See you at 2:00, so, Colm.
On se verra à 14 h.
Why don't you come down for a sherry later?
Viens donc boire un sherry plus tard.
There's no need to be stuck inside on a nice day.
Il fait beau, ne reste pas encabanée.
I will so.
J'irai.
How's the book?
C'est un bon livre ?
It's sad.
Il est triste.
Sad?
Triste ?
Well, you should read a not sad one, Siobhan,
Lis autre chose, sinon ça te rendra triste aussi.
Do you never get lonely, Padraic?
Ne te sens-tu jamais seul, Pádraic ?
Never get what?
Jamais comment ?
Do I never get lonely?
Si je me sens seul ?
What's the matter with everybody?
Qu'est-ce qui vous prend tous ?
Jesus.
Seigneur.
"Lonely." Fecking hell.
"Seul." Bon Dieu.
Colm?
Colm ?
Pint, Jonjo.
Une bière, Jonjo.
How's he seem?
Comment semble-t-il ?
Grand, I think. With me, anyways.
Très bien. Avec moi, du moins.
What are you doing?
Que fais-tu ?
Oh, so you're gonna be an eejit again today, is it?
Tu agis encore en crétin aujourd'hui ?
Amn't I allowed to have a quiet pint on me own, Padraic?
Je ne peux pas boire ma bière en paix ?
Well, don't ask a man to call up to ya at your fecking house, so,
Ne me demande pas de passer chez toi
like he has nothing better to do with his fecking time.
comme si je n'avais rien d'autre à faire.
I didn't ask you to call up to me at me house.
Je ne t'ai pas demandé de passer.
And you do have nothing better to do with your fecking time.
Et tu n'as rien de mieux à faire.
You do have nothing better to do with your fecking time.
Tu n'as rien de mieux à faire de ton temps.
I know I've nothing better to do with me fecking time,
Je sais que je n'ai rien de mieux à faire,
but there's better things I could be doing with me fecking time
mais je pourrais faire autre chose
than to be calling up to ya at your house, Colm Doherty!
que passer chez toi, Colm Doherty !
Like what?
Comme quoi ?
Like what else could you be doin'?
Que pourrais-tu faire d'autre ?
Reading.
Lire.
Reading, yeah?
Lire ?
Me, this morning...
Moi, ce matin,
this I wrote.
j'ai composé ça.
Tomorrow, I'll write the second part of it.
Demain, je composerai la deuxième partie.
And the day after, I'll write the third part of it.
Et après-demain, la troisième.
And by Wednesday, there'll be a new tune in the world,
Mercredi, on aura une nouvelle chanson
which wouldn't have been there if I'd spent the week
qui n'existerait pas si j'avais passé la semaine
listening to your bollocks, Padraic Suilleabhain.
à écouter tes conneries, Pádraic Súilleabháin.
So, do you want to take your pint outside,
Alors, qui va boire sa bière dehors, toi ou moi ?
I'll take my pint outside,
Je boirai la mienne dehors, car c'est une chanson de merde
I wouldn't bother with it.
qui ne m'intéresse pas.
I was too harsh yesterday.
J'ai été trop dur hier.
Yesterday, he says.
Hier, qu'il dit.
I know well you was too harsh yesterday.
Je sais que tu as été trop dur hier.
And today.
Et aujourd'hui.
I just have this tremendous sense of time slippin' away on me, Padraic.
J'ai le sentiment que le temps me file entre les doigts.
And I think I need to spend the time I have left
Je dois passer le temps qu'il me reste à réfléchir et à composer.
Just trying not to listen
Et non à écouter
But I'm sorry about it. I am, like.
Mais j'en suis désolé. Sincèrement.
Are you dying?
Es-tu mourant ?
No, I'm not dying.
Non.
But then you've loads of time.
Tu as tout le temps, alors.
For chatting?
Pour bavarder ?
Aye.For aimless chatting?
- Oui. - Du bavardage inutile ?
Not for aimless chatting. For good, normal chatting.
Pas du bavardage inutile, du bon bavardage normal.
So, we'll keep aimlessly chatting
Continuons à bavarder inutilement, et ma vie continuera à raccourcir.
And in 12 years, I'll die with nothin' to show for it
Dans 12 ans, je mourrai sans avoir rien accompli
bar the chats I've had with a limited man, is that it?
sauf des conversations avec un benêt, c'est ça ?
I said, "Not aimless chatting."
J'ai dit : "Pas du bavardage inutile."
I said, "Good, normal chatting."
J'ai dit : "Du bon bavardage normal."
The other night, two hours you spent talking to me
L'autre soir, tu as passé deux heures à me parler
about the things you found in your little donkey's shite that day.
de ce que tu avais trouvé dans la merde de ton âne.
Two hours, Padraic. I timed it.
Deux heures, Pádraic. J'ai compté.
Well, it wasn't me little donkey's shite, was it?
Ce n'était pas la merde de mon âne,
It was me pony's shite, which shows how much you were listenin'.
mais de mon poney, ce qui prouve que tu n'écoutais pas.
None of it helps me, do you understand?
Rien de ça ne m'aide, comprends-tu ?
None of it helps me.
Rien de ça ne m'aide.
We'll just chat about somethin' else then.
Parlons d'autre chose, alors.
What's the matter with ya?
Qu'est-ce que tu as ?
Nothin'.
Rien.
Aren't we going for a sherry?
On ne va pas boire un sherry ?
Don't feel like it.
Je n'en ai pas envie.
No, I'm not having this again today!
Non, pas encore ça aujourd'hui !
Hey! What the hell's going on with you and me fecking brother?
Que se passe-t-il entre mon frère et toi ?
Don't come in here shouting the odds at me
Ne viens pas me crier après
in the middle of the fecking day, all right, Siobhan?
au beau milieu de la journée, Siobhán.
You can't just all of a sudden
On ne repousse pas un ami du jour au lendemain !
Why can't I?
Pourquoi pas ?
Why can't ya? Because it isn't nice.
Parce que ce n'est pas gentil.
Do you want a sherry, Siobhan?
- Un sherry, Siobhán ? - Non !
No!Righty-ho.
Très bien.
Has he said somethin' to ya when he was drunk?
T'a-t-il insulté quand il était soûl ?
No, I prefer him when he's drunk.
Non, je le préfère soûl.
It's all the rest of the time I have the problem with.
C'est le reste du temps, le problème.
What's the fecking matter, then?
Où est le problème, au juste ?
He's dull, Siobhan.
Il est ennuyeux, Siobhán.
He's what?
Il est quoi ?
He's dull.
Ennuyeux.
But he's always been dull. What's changed?
Mais il l'a toujours été. Qu'est-ce qui a changé ?
I've changed.
Moi, j'ai changé.
I just don't have a place for dullness in me life anymore.
Je n'ai plus de place pour l'ennui dans ma vie.
But you live on an island off the coast of Ireland, Colm.
Tu habites une île au large de l'Irlande.
What the hell are you hoping for, like?
Qu'espères-tu au juste ?
For a bit of peace, Siobhan. That's all.
Un peu de quiétude. C'est tout.
For a bit of peace in me heart, like.
De la quiétude dans mon cœur.
You can understand that. Can't ya?
Tu peux comprendre ça, n'est-ce pas ?
Do you think I'm dull?
Me trouves-tu ennuyeux ?
No. 'Cause you're not dull, you're nice.
Non. Tu n'es pas ennuyeux, tu es gentil.
That's what I thought. I mean, I'm a happy lad.
Je me disais bien. Je suis un gars heureux.
Or I was.
Enfin, je l'étais.
Till me best friend started acting the gilly-gooly.
Avant que mon meilleur ami agisse en nigaud.
It's him, Padraic.
C'est lui, le problème.
Maybe he's just depressed.
Il est peut-être déprimé.
That's what I was thinking, that he's depressed.
C'est ce que je pensais, qu'il est déprimé.
Well, if he is,
Si c'est le cas, il pourrait garder ça pour lui.
You know, push it down, like the rest of us.
Le refouler, comme tout le monde.
- No, Jenny! - Out!
Non, Jenny ! Dehors !
Out!
Dehors !
She just wants a bit of company, Siobhan.
Elle veut de la compagnie.
Animals is for outside, I've told ya.
La place des animaux est dehors.
And people don't be laughing at me behind me back,
Les gens ne rient pas de moi en cachette,
do they?
n'est-ce pas ?
No. Why would they be?
Pourquoi feraient-ils ça ?
They don't think I'm dim or anything?
Ils ne croient pas que je suis idiot ?
Dim?
Idiot ?
No.
Non.
You don't seem very sure about it.
Tu n'as pas l'air certaine.
Of course, I'm sure about it.
Bien sûr que je suis certaine.
Dominic's the dim one on the island, isn't he?
C'est Dominic, l'idiot de l'île.
He is, aye. By miles.
Oui, de loin.
Well, I don't like to judge people
Je n'aime pas juger les gens en ces termes.
In what terms?In order of their dimness.
- Quels termes ? - En termes d'idiotie.
Well, I know you don't. And neither do I, do I?
Je sais. Moi non plus.
But try, like.No!
- Mais essaie. - Non !
I won't try.
Je n'essaierai pas.
There's enough judgy people on this fecking island, so no!
Il y a assez de gens qui jugent les autres ici !
You're not dim!
Tu n'es pas idiot ! Tu es gentil. Passe à autre chose !
I'm as clever as you, anyways.
Je suis aussi malin que toi.
I know that at least.
Ça, je le sais.
Yeah, don't be fecking stupid.
Ne fais pas l'imbécile.
What happened to you?
Que t'est-il arrivé ?
Me daddy discovered the poteen situation.
Mon père a su, pour sa bouteille.
Oh, Jesus, Dominic!
Seigneur, Dominic !
You poor thing, ya.
Pauvre petit.
What the hell was he hittin' you with?
Avec quoi t'a-t-il frappé ?
A kettle was the final thing.
La bouilloire, pour finir. C'est le bec qui a fait mal.
Do you want a ride to church?
On t'emmène à l'église ?
Uh, feck them gobshites!
Au diable tout ça !
Dominic!
Dominic !
But could I stay the night with ye the night?
Mais puis-je passer la nuit chez vous ?
Just for the one night, like?
Juste une nuit ?
Well, just the one night, mind.
D'accord, mais juste une nuit.
Nice! I'll see ye for supper, so.
Parfait ! On se verra au souper.
Forgive me, Father, for I have sinned.
Pardon, mon père, car j'ai péché.
It's eight weeks since my last confession, I think.
Ma dernière confession remonte à huit semaines.
Go on, Colm.
Je vous écoute, Colm.
Just the usual, I suppose, Father.
Les trucs habituels, mon père. L'alcool, les pensées impures.
And a bit of pride, I suppose.
Un peu d'orgueil.
Although I never really saw that as a sin, but sure I'm here now.
Je n'ai jamais vu ça comme un péché, mais me voici.
And
Et...
how's the despair?
Comment va le désespoir ?
Not so much of it of late. Thanks be.
Je n'en ressens pas dernièrement, Dieu merci.
And why aren't you talking to Padraic Suilleabhain no more?
Pourquoi ignorez-vous Pádraic Súilleabháin ?
That wouldn't be a sin, now, would it, Father?
Est-ce un péché, mon père ?
It wouldn't be a sin, no, but it's not very nice either, is it?
Non, mais ce n'est pas très gentil non plus.
Who told you?
Qui vous l'a dit ?
It's an island, Colm. Word gets around.
C'est une île, Colm. Les nouvelles se répandent.
Also, Padraic asked me to put in a word, like.
Et puis, Pádraic m'a demandé d'en glisser un mot.
I see.
Je vois.
So...
Alors...
It isn't him you have the impure thoughts about, is it?
C'est à propos de lui, vos pensées impures ?
Are you joking me?
Vous plaisantez ?
I mean, are you fecking joking me?
C'est une maudite blague ?
People do have impure thoughts about men, too.
C'est possible d'avoir des pensées impures à propos d'hommes.
Do you have impure thoughts about men, Father?
En avez-vous, mon père ?
I do not have impure thoughts about men.
Je n'ai pas de pensées impures à propos d'hommes.
And how dare you say that about a man of the cloth?
Comment osez-vous demander ça à un prêtre ?
Well, you started it.
C'est vous qui avez commencé.
Well, you can get out of my confessional right now, so you can.
Sortez de mon confessionnal immédiatement.
And I'm not forgiving you any of these things
Je ne vous pardonne rien jusqu'à la prochaine fois !
I'll be pure fucked!
Je serai foutu !
You will be pure fucked!
Vous serez foutu !
Yes, you will be pure fucked!
Oui, vous serez foutu !
Pint, Colm?
Une bière, Colm ?
If you don't stop talkin' to me,
Si tu n'arrêtes pas de me parler et de m'embêter
or sendin' your sister or your priest to bother me...
ou d'envoyer ta sœur ou ton prêtre m'embêter...
I didn't send me sister to bother you, did I?
Je n'ai pas envoyé ma sœur.
She has her own mind.
Elle fait ce qu'elle veut.
Although, I did send the priest though, you have me there.
Le prêtre, oui, je l'avoue.
What I've decided to do is this.
Voici ce que j'ai décidé.
I have a set of shears at home.
J'ai des cisailles chez moi.
And each time you bother me from this day on,
Dès aujourd'hui, chaque fois que tu m'embêteras,
I'll take those shears
je prendrai ces cisailles
and I'll take one of me fingers off with them.
pour me couper un doigt.
And I'll give that finger to ya.
Et je te donnerai ce doigt.
A finger from me left hand. Me fiddle hand.
Un doigt de ma main gauche, celle du violon.
And each day you bother me more,
Chaque jour où tu m'embêteras,
another I'll take off and I'll give ya
j'en couperai un autre pour te le donner
until you see sense enough to stop.
jusqu'à ce que tu aies la jugeote d'arrêter.
Or until I have no fingers left.
Ou que je n'aie plus de doigts.
Does this make things clearer to ya?
Ça clarifie les choses ?
Not really, no.
Pas vraiment, non.
Because I don't want
Je ne veux pas te faire de peine.
I don't, like.
Sincèrement.
But it feels like the drastic
Mais il ne me reste que la solution radicale.
You've loads of options left open to ya.
Il y a plein d'autres solutions.
How's fingers the first port of call?
Pourquoi passer directement aux doigts ?
Please, don't talk to me
S'il te plaît, arrête de me parler.
no more, Padraic. Please.
Arrête, Pádraic. S'il te plaît.
I'm begging you.
- Je t'en prie. - Mais...
But...JONJO: Shush, like, Padraic.
Tais-toi, Pádraic.
Just, you know, shush, like.Yeah, I'd shush, like.
- Plus un mot. - Moi, je me tairais.
I will shush.
Je me tairai.
Except me and me sister were thinking
Ma sœur et moi, on se disait que tu es peut-être déprimé, Colm.
And I tell you this much, fingers just confirms it.
Je vais te dire une chose : cette histoire de doigts le confirme.
Don't you think, Colm?
Ne crois-tu pas ?
Starting from now.
Ça commence maintenant.
Well, I never heard the like.
Je n'ai jamais rien entendu de tel.
I never heard the like. He must really not like you, Padraic.
Tu dois vraiment lui déplaire, Pádraic.
Fingers!
Ses doigts !
Jesus. He's serious, lads.
Il est sérieux, les gars.
He is serious!
Il est sérieux !
You can see it in his eyes he's serious.
Ça se voit dans ses yeux.
Just because he thinks you're dull.
Juste parce qu'il te trouve ennuyeux.
That's going overboard!
Il y va trop fort !
Who told you about the dull?
Qui t'a dit que j'étais ennuyeux ?
Well, I overheard it.
J'ai entendu ça au passage. Que devais-je faire ?
I don't think you're dull.
Je ne te trouve pas ennuyeux.
And jeez, if I was to cut something off meself
Si je me coupais une partie du corps
for every dull person that came in here, I'd only have me head left.
pour chaque personne ennuyeuse ici, il ne resterait que ma tête.
Do you think I'm dull, Gerry?
Me trouves-tu ennuyeux, Gerry ?
No.
Non.
That said,
Cela dit...
I did think the two of ye always made a funny pairing, like.
Je trouvais que vous formiez un drôle de duo.
No, we didn't.JONJO: Yeah, ye did.
- Mais non. - Mais oui.
Ye did. Obviously, ye did.
C'est évident que oui.
'Cause now he'd rather maim himself than talk to ya.
Il se mutilerait plutôt que de te parler.
Colm was always more of a thinker.
Colm a toujours été un penseur.
Why's every... I think.
Pourquoi est-ce... Je pense.
Ah, you don't, Padraic.
Non, Pádraic.
You don't, Padraic.Your sister does.
- Non. - Ta sœur, oui.
Your sister does, aye. Siobhan does.You're more of a...
- C'est une penseuse. - Tu es plutôt...
You're more of a... What is he?
Plutôt... Qu'est-il ?
You're more one of life's good guys.
Un chic type, tout simplement.
You're more one of life's good guys, aye.
Un chic type, oui. Sauf quand tu es soûl.
Apart from when you're drunk, aye.
Sauf quand tu es soûl, oui.
I used to think that'd be a nice thing to be.
Avant, je croyais que ce serait bien
One of life's good guys.
d'être un chic type.
And now, it sounds like the worst thing I ever heard.
À présent, c'est ce que j'ai entendu de pire.
Ah, don't take it like that, Padraic.
Ne le prends pas mal.
We're on your side.
On est dans ton camp.
What are you smiling at?
Qu'est-ce qui vous fait sourire ?
What's this mope so mopey for? He's just a fecking man, lads!
Pourquoi boude-t-il comme ça ? C'est juste un homme !
A fat, ginger man!
Un homme roux et gras !
Ay yi yi.
Aïe, aïe, aïe.
I'll tell ya this much. Ye two are awful mopey hosts.
En tout cas, vous êtes deux hôtes boudeurs.
Luckily, you won't have to put up with us more than one night, so,
Tu n'auras à nous endurer que pour une nuit.
and try eatin' with your mouth closed.
Ferme la bouche quand tu mastiques.
Where are we now, France?
On est en France ou quoi ?
Will you tell him, Padraic?
Peux-tu lui dire ?
Aye, stop being a little fecking bollocks, Dominic.
Arrête de faire le petit con, Dominic.
No. Just about the mouth thing.
Non, juste à propos de sa bouche.
Colm Doherty and his fat fecking fingers.
Colm Doherty et ses gros doigts de merde.
He probably wouldn't even be able
Je parie qu'il n'arriverait pas à couper dans le gras.
Would you not want him to have to do the one finger
Voulez-vous qu'il se coupe un doigt pour voir s'il bluffe ?
No, we wouldn't.
Pas du tout.
That's what I'd have him do,
Moi, je voudrais qu'il s'en coupe un pour voir s'il bluffe.
'Cause worst comes to worst,
Au pire,
Or the banjo.
Ou du banjo.
We don't want any of that.
On ne veut pas ça. On ne veut plus avoir affaire à lui.
You don't. This gom does.
Toi, non. Mais cet idiot, oui.
I am a gom, is right.
Je suis idiot, oui.
You're not a gom!
Mais non !
Jeez.
Seigneur.
This is a depressing house.
C'est déprimant, ici.
Would you prefer your own, so?
Préfères-tu rentrer chez toi ?
I've heard it's a barrel of fecking laughs.
Il paraît qu'on y rigole bien.
Well, touche.
Touché.
Too what?
Tout quoi ?
Che. Touche. It's from the French.
Touché. C'est une expression.
And how is it, Siobhan, that you was never married?
Pourquoi ne t'es-tu jamais mariée ?
It's none of your fecking business
Ce n'est pas de tes affaires que je ne sois pas mariée.
How isn't it?
Ah non ?
Was you never wild?
N'as-tu jamais été sauvage ?
Wild? Was I never wild?
Si j'ai été sauvage ?
I don't know what you're talkin' about, Dominic.
Qu'est-ce que tu racontes ?
Wild, how? Angry?
Sauvage ? Veux-tu que je me fâche ?
'Cause I'm gettin' angry now, I can tell ya!
Si c'est le cas, c'est réussi !
Not angry. Wild.
Pas fâchée, sauvage.
You just keep sayin' wild, Dominic!
Tu n'arrêtes pas de dire ça !
Wild!My brother told you, didn't he?
- Sauvage ! - Mon frère t'a averti, non ?
That you'd be out in the road
Que tu coucherais dehors si tu disais des bêtises ?
He said creepy, not stupid.
Des grossièretés, pas des bêtises.
I have.
Je l'avoue.
I'm off to bed and he's not stayin' here another night, Padraic.
Je vais me coucher. Il ne restera pas une nuit de plus.
I don't care how depressed you are.
Je me fiche que tu sois déprimé. Je lui préfère l'âne.
Foiled again.
Un autre échec.
But "faint heart" and all that.
Mais "à cœur vaillant" et tout ça.
Here.
Écoute.
Ye two, ye'll be all right.
Ça ira pour vous deux.
Will we be?
Vraiment ?
Hello there, Mrs. O'Riordan, I've the milk outside for ya.
Bonjour, Mme O'Riordan. J'ai votre lait.
So, it's the two weeks you owe me for now, I think.
Vous me devez deux semaines, je crois.
Nobody has a lick of news
Personne ne donne de nouvelles de ton côté de l'île, Pádraic.
Are you going to be the same as them?
Vas-tu faire pareil ?
I am, Mrs. O'Riordan, I'm afraid.
J'ai bien peur que oui. Je suis pressé, alors...
Eileen Coughlan had no news.
Eileen Coughlan n'avait pas de nouvelles.
Vincent Shaughnessy had no news.
Vincent Shaughnessy, pas de nouvelles.
It was a poor old week for news. But then it is, sometimes.
La semaine a été tranquille. C'est ainsi.
ColmSonnyLarry, he had no news.
ColmSonnyLarry n'avait pas de nouvelles.
Did he not?
Ah bon ?
That man never talks.
Il ne parle jamais.
Eh, he talks sometimes.Up himself.
- Il parle parfois. - Il se parle.
Aye, aye, anyways, so, it's the two weeks you owe me for now, Mrs. O'Riordan.
Peu importe, vous me devez deux semaines.
As I was sayin'.
Comme je disais.
Ladies.
Mesdames.
Oh, it's Peadar.
C'est Peadar.
Peadar always has a rake of news.
Il a toujours plein de nouvelles.
What news have you, Peadar?PEADAR: News, is it?
- Quelles nouvelles, Peadar ? - Des nouvelles ?
Fella killed himself, over Rosmuck way.
Un homme s'est suicidé près de Rosmuck.
Walked into a lake for himself.
Il s'est englouti dans un lac.
Twenty-nine and nothing wrong with him, the fool.
Vingt-neuf ans et en bonne santé, l'imbécile.
God love us!
Dieu ait pitié !
No, not "God love us." Fool!
Pas de "Dieu ait pitié". L'imbécile !
Another fella,
Un autre homme...
Protestant, of course,
Un protestant, bien sûr.
stabbed his missus in Letterkenny.
Il a poignardé sa femme à Letterkenny.
Six times he stabbed her.
Six fois.
Good God! And did she die, Peadar?
Pour l'amour ! Est-elle morte, Peadar ?
She did die, aye.
Elle est morte, oui.
It wasn't with a spoon he was stabbin' her.
Il ne l'a pas poignardée avec une cuillère.
That's a lot of news.
Ça fait beaucoup de nouvelles.
This man has no news, don't ya not? No-Newsy!
Celui-là n'en avait pas. Pas de nouvelles !
Stukes never have news.MRS. O'RIORDAN: Stukes!
- Les bêtas n'en ont jamais. - Les bêtas !
Funny.
C'est drôle.
There was a bit of news I remembered, Mrs. O'Riordan.
Je viens de penser à une nouvelle, Mme O'Riordan.
Dominic Kearney's father beat Dominic senseless
Le père de Dominic Kearney l'a battu avec une bouilloire samedi.
and is staying with me and me sister, Dominic is.
Dominic loge chez nous.
So, at least his father'll take a bit of a break
Comme ça, son père ne le battra pas pendant un moment.
And him, a policeman.
Un policier, en plus.
Isn't that news?
Toute une nouvelle, non ?
Ar, that Dominic's an awful little bollocks.
Ce Dominic est un horrible petit crétin.
That's no news.
Ce n'est pas une nouvelle.
Still, he was in a bad way when I came upon him.
Il était mal en point quand je l'ai trouvé.
I'd beat him with a kettle meself if I wasn't old.
Je le battrais moi-même si j'étais jeune.
It's news is all I'm sayin'.
C'est une nouvelle.
Okay, so, Mrs. O'Riordan, thanks for the...
Bon, Mme O'Riordan, merci pour...
I'll see ya when I see ya.
On se verra plus tard.
And you can tell that skitter of a son of mine
Et dis à mon imbécile de fils
he'd better be home by teatime,
de rentrer pour le thé,
or it's over to batter the both of ye I'll be,
sinon je vous tabasse tous les deux
and your dreary fecking sister, too!
et ta grognasse de sœur aussi !
Oh, hello there, Colm.
Bonjour, Colm.
Will I see you at Jonjo's tonight for that pint you owe me?
On se verra chez Jonjo pour la bière que tu me dois ?
I owe you no pin...
Je ne te dois pas...
You will, Peadar.
Oui, Peadar.
Good man yourself.
Brave homme.
What's that, Jenny?
Que dis-tu, Jenny ?
Will we go to the pub for ourselves?
Aller au pub tous les deux ?
We will. Come on.
Faisons ça. Viens.
One drink you're havin', lady, then it's off home with ya.
Juste un verre, fillette, puis tu rentres.
I've a shirt that wants ironing for the morning.
J'ai une chemise à faire repasser.
Okay, Daddy.
D'accord, papa.
Aye. Off to the mainland in the morning I'm headin'.
Je pars pour la grande île au matin.
That's why I need the clean shirt, like.
Il me faut une chemise propre.
"And why are you off to the mainland in the mornin', Peadar?"
"Pourquoi pars-tu pour la grande île au matin ?"
Oh, thanks for asking, Colm. I'll tell ya why.
Merci de le demander. Je vais te le dire.
They've asked for extra manpower
Ils ont besoin de renforts pour quelques exécutions,
in case there's any kind of a to-do, like.
au cas où il y aurait des émeutes.
Six bob and a free lunch they're payin' me.
Ils m'offrent six shillings et le dîner.
And sure I'd have gone for nothin'.
Mais j'y serais allé pour rien.
I've always wanted to see an execution, haven't you?
J'ai toujours voulu voir une exécution. Pas toi ?
Although, I'd have preferred a hanging.
J'aurais préféré une pendaison.
Who are they executin'?
Qui vont-ils exécuter ?
The Free State lads are executin' a couple of the IRA lads.
Des gars de l'État libre exécutent des gars de l'IRA.
Or is it the other way around?
Ou est-ce le contraire ?
I find it hard to follow these days.
C'est dur à suivre ces jours-ci.
Wasn't it so much easier when we was all on the same side,
C'était plus facile d'être du même camp
and it was just the English we was killin'?
et de tuer seulement des Anglais, non ?
I think it was. I preferred it.
Je crois que oui. Je préférais ça.
But you don't care who's executin' who?
Qui exécute qui, tu t'en fiches ?
For six bob and a free lunch, I don't care!
Pour six shillings et un dîner, je m'en fiche !
They could be executin' you.
Ça pourrait être toi qui y passes.
Why don't you come with me?
Et si tu m'accompagnais ?
You could write a miserable feckin' song about it.
Ça pourrait t'inspirer une chanson triste.
Nah, I'm only messin'.
Non, je plaisante.
Who are them?
Qui sont-ils ?
Music students, I think, from Lisdoonvarna.
Des étudiants en musique de Lisdoonvarna.
Another whisky, anyways, Jonjo.
Un autre whisky, Jonjo.
Jeez, you're goin' at it at a fair old lick tonight, Padraic.
Tu y vas fort ce soir, Pádraic.
Yeah? What's it to ya?
Et alors ? En quoi ça t'importe ?
Padraic, don't now...
Pádraic, non...
Go get Siobhan, Dominic, would ya?
Dominic, va chercher Siobhán.
What are you after, gobshite?
Que veux-tu, l'abruti ?
Another beatin', is it?
Une autre raclée ?
You, copper, I'm allowed to chat to you, aren't I?
Toi, le policier, je peux te parler, non ?
It's just tubbyguts I'm not allowed to talk to.
C'est au gros lard que je ne dois rien dire.
Actually, no, I'd rather you didn't talk to me neither.
Je préfère que tu ne me parles pas non plus.
do you want to know what the three things that I hate the most
Veux-tu connaître les trois choses que je déteste le plus
on Inisherin is? Not really.
- d'Inisherin ? - Pas vraiment.
One,
De un,
policemen.
les policiers.
Two,
De deux,
pudgy fiddle players.
les violonistes dodus.
And three...
Et de trois...
Wait, I had some funny thing for three. What was it?
J'avais un truc rigolo. Quoi, déjà ?
Uh, I'll start again. One, um,
Je recommence. De un,
policemen.
les policiers.
Two...
De deux...
Pudgy fiddle players.
Les violonistes dodus.
And shite, what was three?
Merde, c'était quoi, la troisième ?
Serious, are ya?
Sérieux, hein ?
And talkin' to me, are ya?
Et tu me parles, hein ?
Siobhan!
Siobhán !
Padraic's out of his brains on whisky, and Colm's there.
Pádraic se défonce au whisky, et Colm est là.
You'd better come.
Tu devrais venir.
You, Colm Doherty, do you know what you used to be?
Colm Doherty, sais-tu ce que tu étais ?
No, Padraic, what did I used to be?
Non, qu'est-ce que j'étais ?
Nice!
Gentil !
You used to be nice!
Tu étais gentil !
Didn't he not?
Il l'était, non ?
And now, do you know what you are?
Et à présent, sais-tu ce que tu es ?
Not nice.
Pas gentil.
Ah, well,
Bon...
I suppose niceness doesn't last then, does it, Padraic?
J'imagine que la gentillesse ne dure pas.
But will I tell ya something that does last?
Mais sais-tu ce qui dure ?
What? And don't say somethin' stupid like music.
Quoi ? Ne dis pas un truc idiot comme la musique.
Music lasts.Knew it!
- La musique. - Je le savais !
And paintings last. And poetry lasts.
La peinture. La poésie.
So does niceness.
La gentillesse aussi.
Do you know who we remember
Qui se rappelle-t-on
for how nice they was in the 17th century?
pour sa gentillesse au XVIIe siècle ?
Who? Absolutely no one.
- Qui ? - Absolument personne.
Yet we all remember the music of the time.
Mais on se rappelle la musique de l'époque.
Everyone, to a man, knows Mozart's name.
Tout le monde connaît Mozart.
Well, I don't, so there goes that theory.
Pas moi, alors au diable ta théorie.
And anyway, we're talkin' about niceness.
Et puis, on parlait de gentillesse.
Not whatsisname.
Pas de ce type.
My mammy, she was nice.
Ma mère était gentille.
I remember her.
Je m'en souviens.
And my daddy, he was nice. I remember him.
Mon père était gentil. Je m'en souviens.
And my sister, she's nice.
Ma sœur est gentille.
I'll remember her. Forever I'll remember her.
Je m'en souviendrai. Pour toujours.
And who else will? PADRAIC: "Who else will" what?
- Et qui d'autre ? - Qui d'autre quoi ?
Remember Siobhan and your niceness?
Se rappellera Siobhán et ta gentillesse ?
No one will.
Personne.
In 50 years' time,
Dans 50 ans,
no one will remember any of us.
on sera tous oubliés.
Yet the music of a man who lived two centuries ago...
Pourtant, la musique d'un homme d'il y a deux siècles...
"Yet," he says, like he's English.
Écoutez-le avec ses grands mots.
Come home, Padraic.
Rentrons, Pádraic.
I don't give a feck about Mozart,
Je me fiche de Mozart,
or Borvoven,
de Borvoven
or any of them funny name feckers.
et de tous ces crétins au drôle de nom.
I'm Padraic Suilleabhain.
Je suis Pádraic Súilleabháin.
And I'm nice.
Et je suis gentil.
Come home.
Rentrons.
So you'd rather be friends with this fella, would ya?
Tu préfères être l'ami de cet homme ?
A fella who
Un homme
beats his own son black and blue every night
qui couvre son fils de bleus chaque soir sauf quand il le tripote.
I never told him that, Daddy. He's... He's just drunk now.
Je ne lui ai jamais dit ça, papa. Il est soûl.
You used to be nice.
Tu étais gentil.
Or did you never used to be?
À moins que tu ne l'aies jamais été ?
Oh, God.
Seigneur.
Maybe you never used to be.
Tu ne l'as peut-être jamais été.
I'll have a word with him, Colm.
Je vais lui parler, Colm. Ne fais rien d'irréparable.
He won't be botherin' you no more.
Il ne t'embêtera plus.
That's a shame.
Dommage.
That's the most interesting he's ever been.
Il n'a jamais été aussi intéressant. Je recommence à bien l'aimer.
It was the 18th century, anyway. Mozart.
Mozart a vécu au XVIIIe siècle.
Not the 17th.
Pas au XVIIe.
Siobhan Suilleabhain! Well, well.
Siobhán Súilleabháin ! Eh bien.
I only came in for rashers, Mrs. O'Riordan.
Je viens acheter du bacon, Mme O'Riordan. Pas le temps de bavarder.
Letter came for ya.
Tu as reçu une lettre.
Fell open, did it?
Elle s'est ouverte en tombant ?
Aye, in the heat, I suppose.
C'est la chaleur, j'imagine.
A job offer, is it?
Une offre d'emploi, c'est ça ?
A job offer from a library on the mainland, is it?
D'une bibliothèque sur la grande île ?
Just the rashers, please, Mrs. O'Riordan. About ten of them.
Juste le bacon, je vous prie, Mme O'Riordan. Dix tranches.
You never tell me anything!
Tu ne me dis jamais rien !
Well, it'd crucify him, your leaving!
Si tu pars, il en mourra !
Hey, no one's leaving!
Personne ne part !
Listen, I didn't come down to chat.
Je ne suis pas venu bavarder.
I just came down to say that all that last night
Tout ça, hier soir, c'était le whisky qui parlait.
All what last night?
Tout quoi hier soir ?
All whatever it was I was sayin'.
Tout ce que j'ai raconté.
What were you sayin'?
Qu'as-tu raconté ?
but I remember the gist of it wasn't the best.
mais je sais que ce n'était pas génial.
You always know, don't ya?
Tu le sais, n'est-ce pas ?
Well, anyways, I just wanted to say I was sorry.
Peu importe, je voulais simplement m'excuser.
Will we leave it at that?
Peut-on en rester là ?
Why can't you just leave me alone, Padraic?
Pourquoi ne me laisses-tu pas tranquille ?
I've already told ya, haven't I?
Je t'ai averti, non ?
Yeah, I know. I was just...
Je sais, j'étais juste...
I mean, why can't you just leave me alone?
Pourquoi ne me laisses-tu pas tranquille ?
What are ya doing?I don't know.
- Que fais-tu ? - Je ne sais pas.
For fuck's sake, like.
Pour l'amour !
How... How's the new tune?
Ça avance, ta chanson ?
What?
Quoi ?
Ar, for God's sake, Padraic.
Bon Dieu, Pádraic.
How many more times?
Combien de fois encore ?
I am not putting me donkey outside when I am sad, okay?
Je ne fais pas sortir mon âne quand je suis triste.
Well, stringy bits of shite I had to pick up
J'ai dû ramasser des brins de merde quand tu l'as fait entrer hier !
There was no stringy bits in that donkey's shite.
Non, pas des brins de merde.
There was bits of straw, if there was anything.
Peut-être un peu de paille, c'est tout.
Maybe it was straw, so.
C'était peut-être de la paille.
Was I awful last night?
Ai-je été terrible, hier soir ?
No, you was lovely.
Non, tu étais charmant.
Well, I know I wasn't lovely now, Siobhan.
Je sais que c'est faux, Siobhán.
You were lovely. About me, anyways.
Charmant avec moi, du moins.
Of course I was lovely about you.
Avec toi, bien sûr.
What else is there to be about ya?
Comment faire autrement ?
What was that? A bird?
C'était quoi ? Un oiseau ?
What was what?
C'était quoi ?
The bang at the door.
Le coup sur la porte.
A bird?
Un oiseau ?
Aye.No.
- Oui. - Non.
What was it, so?
C'était quoi, alors ?
The bang at the door?Aye!
- Le coup sur la porte ? - Oui !
What was the bang at the door?
C'était quoi, le coup sur la porte ?
It was, uh...
C'était...
hard to lie...
Difficile de mentir...
A what?
Un quoi ?
Jesus, Siobhan! You'll frighten the little fella!
Seigneur, Siobhán ! Tu fais peur à l'âne !
Throw it out, Padraic!
Jette-le, Pádraic !
I'm not throwing his finger out! It'll get dirt on it!
Je ne jetterai pas son doigt ! Ça le salirait !
Where... Where'd you put it?
Où l'as-tu mis ?
Shoebox.
Dans une boîte à chaussures.
Oh, my. Oh, God.
Mon Dieu.
Well,
Bon...
he's serious, then.
Il est sérieux, alors.
Do we have to have it in here while we're eating?
Doit-il rester là pendant le repas ?
Once I finish me porridge, I'll bring it back to him.
Je le lui rapporterai après mon gruau.
I mean, are you feckin' stupid?
Sérieusement, es-tu stupide ?
No, I'm not feckin' stupid. We've had this discussion.
Non. On en a déjà parlé.
You've got to leave him alone now, Padraic. For good!
Tu dois le laisser tranquille. Pour de bon !
Do you think?
Tu crois ?
Do I think? Yeah, I do think!
Oui, je crois !
He's cut his feckin' finger off, and thrown it at ya!
Il s'est coupé un doigt et te l'a lancé dessus !
Come on! It wasn't at me.
Il ne me l'a pas lancé dessus.
Well, what are we going to do?
Qu'est-ce qu'on va faire ?
We can't keep a man's finger.
On ne peut pas garder son doigt.
Jesus, Colm!
Seigneur, Colm !
Did it hurt?
Ça t'a fait mal ?
Hurt awful to begin with. Thought I was going to faint.
Beaucoup, au début. J'ai cru m'évanouir.
It's funny, feels fine now, in all the excitement.
C'est drôle, je ne le sens plus avec tout cet énervement.
Would you like a cup of tea?
Je t'offre du thé ?
I won't, Colm. I only came up to give you your finger back.
Non, Colm. Je viens seulement te rapporter ton doigt.
Oh, yeah?
Ah oui ?
Thanks.
Merci.
Cleared up quite nice, actually.
Il fait beau, finalement.
And you wouldn't have thought it would.
On n'aurait pas cru ça.
What do you need from him, Colm?
Que veux-tu de lui, Colm ?
To end all this?
Pour arrêter tout ça ?
Silence, Siobhan.
Du silence, Siobhán.
Just silence.
Rien que du silence.
One more silent man on Inisherin, good-oh!
Un homme silencieux de plus à Inisherin, fantastique !
Silence it is, so.
Du silence, alors.
This isn't about Inisherin.
Il n'est pas question d'Inisherin,
It's about one boring man
mais d'un homme ennuyeux qui laisse un autre homme tranquille.
"One boring man"! You're all fecking boring!
"Un homme ennuyeux" ! Vous êtes tous ennuyeux !
With your piddling grievances over nothin'!
Vous et vos plaintes minables à propos de rien !
I'll see he doesn't talk to you no more.
Je veillerai à ce qu'il ne te parle plus.
Do.
Fais ça.
Else it'll be all four of them the next time, not just the one.
Sinon, les quatre doigts restants y passeront la prochaine fois.
You're not serious.
Tu n'es pas sérieux.
Well, that won't help your fecking music.
Ça ne t'aidera pas avec ta musique.
Aye.
C'est sûr.
We're gettin' somewhere now.
On se comprend enfin.
Do worry sometimes I'm just entertaining meself
Je m'inquiète parfois de me faire des illusions
while I stave off the inevitable.
en retardant l'inévitable.
Don't you?
Pas toi ?
No, I don't.
Non.
Yeah, you do.
Bien sûr que oui.
Declan!
Declan !
Howdo!
Bonjour !
Do you want a ride?
Voulez-vous monter ?
I will so.
D'accord.
Thanks, fella!
Merci, l'ami !
Oh, no, you're not that student fella from Lisdoonvarna, are ya?
Vous ne seriez pas l'étudiant de Lisdoonvarna ?
I am. I'm Declan.
Oui. Je m'appelle Declan.
Why?
Pourquoi ?
They told me at the post office to try to find
On m'a dit au bureau de poste de chercher
that student fella, Declan, from Lisdoonvarna.
l'étudiant de Lisdoonvarna, Declan.
Yeah, a telegram came for ya.
Vous avez reçu un télégramme
From your mammy.
de votre mère.
My mammy is no longer with us.
Elle n'est plus de ce monde.
Not your mammy, sorry.
Pas votre mère, pardon.
Did I say your mammy? Your auntie. Yeah, your auntie.
Ai-je dit votre mère ? Votre tante.
It's about your daddy.
À propos de votre père.
What about Daddy?
Qu'est-ce qu'il a ?
The bread van?Yeah.
- Le camion à pain ? - Oui.
They said you'd best hurry home to him, lest he should die all alone.
Rentrez vite chez vous pour qu'il ne meure pas seul.
Die?
Qu'il meure ?
Or get worse, all alone.
Ou que son état empire, seul.
This is impossible.
C'est impossible.
It's not impossible.
Ce n'est pas impossible.
Bread vans crash into people all the time.
- Ça arrive, les accidents de camion. - Je sais !
That's how me mammy died.
C'est comme ça que ma mère est morte.
If it's the same fecking bread van, I'll kill them.
Si c'est le même camion à pain, je les tuerai.
Thanks.
Merci.
What were you talking to the boat fella for?
Pourquoi parlais-tu au type du bateau ?
For none of your fecking business, I think it was.
Ça ne te regarde pas.
Of course, it's me business. Aren't I the law?
Bien sûr que oui. Je représente la loi.
Fecking knob.
Enfoiré.
Well, you can tell that whiny brother of yours
Dis à ton chialeux de frère
I'll be around soon for that battering I owe him.
que je lui donnerai bientôt la raclée promise.
A battering?
Une raclée ?
That'd be good, actually. It might take him out of himself.
C'est bien, en fait. Ça lui replacera les idées.
You're an awful strange lady.
Tu es drôlement bizarre.
No wonder no one likes ya.
Pas étonnant que personne ne t'aime.
Hello there, Mrs. McCormick.
Bonjour, Mme McCormick.
A death shall come to Inisherin afore the month is out.
La mort viendra à Inisherin avant la fin du mois.
A death, huh?
La mort, hein ?
Maybe even two deaths.
Peut-être même deux fois.
Well, that'd be sad.
Ce serait triste.
We shall pray to the Lord
Prions le Seigneur
'tis neither you, nor poor Siobhan, will be either of them.
que ça ne soit pas toi ni la pauvre Siobhán.
Well, is that a nice thing to be sayin'?
Est-ce une chose gentille à dire ?
I wasn't trying to be nice.
Je n'essayais pas d'être gentille.
I was trying to be accurate.
J'essayais d'être précise.
Fecking hell.
Maudit bordel.
What's the matter?
Que se passe-t-il ?
Nothing.
Rien.
Me daddy say he's gonna kill you Sunday
Mon père dit qu'il te tuera dimanche
for spilling the beans about that fiddling with me.
pour avoir révélé qu'il me tripote.
"Kill me," kill me, or, you know,
Me tuer pour vrai ou juste...
"beat me up a bit," kill me?
"Me tuer" en me tabassant un peu ?
"Beat you up a bit," kill ya, I think.
Te tabasser un peu, je crois.
Although he did kill a man once.
Mais il a déjà tué un homme.
I'm sorry for that spilling the beans on ya, Dominic.
Je regrette d'avoir parlé de ça.
I was out of order that night.
J'étais déchaîné ce soir-là.
You was funny apart from that bit.
Tu étais drôle, sauf pour ça.
That's why I don't understand why that fat fella threw the finger at ya.
Je ne comprends pas pourquoi le gros t'a lancé son doigt.
He seemed fine when you were slagging him.
Tes insultes ne semblaient pas le déranger.
Did he?
Tu crois ?
"I think I like him again now."
"Je recommence à bien l'aimer."
Aye.
Eh bien.
Maybe this whole thing has just been about gettin' you to try a new tack,
Peut-être qu'il voulait juste que tu changes d'attitude,
start standin' up for yourself a bit.
que tu t'affirmes un peu.
Do you think?
Penses-tu ?
Yeah, and be less of a, you know,
Oui, que tu sois moins
whiny little dull-arse.
ennuyeux et chialeux.
Well, I have been less of a whiny little dull-arse, actually.
C'est vrai que je le suis moins.
Have ya, yeah?
Ah bon ?
Just yesterday, there was this musician fella
Hier, j'ai croisé le musicien avec lequel Colm s'entendait bien.
And what did I do?
Et qu'ai-je fait ? Je l'ai chassé de l'île.
Did ya? How?
Tu as fait ça ? Comment ?
I told him a bread van crashed into his daddy,
J'ai dit qu'un camion avait renversé son père
and he'd have to be rushing home to him, lest he die.
et qu'il devait rentrer avant qu'il meure.
That sounds like the meanest thing I've ever heard.
Je n'ai jamais rien entendu d'aussi méchant.
Well, aye, it was a bit mean, but...
C'était un peu méchant, oui, mais...
he'll be fine once he gets home
Il s'en remettra quand il verra que son père n'a rien.
I used to think you were the nicest of them.
Je te croyais plus gentil que les autres.
Turns out you're just the same as them.
Finalement, tu es comme eux.
I am the nicest of them.
Je suis plus gentil que les autres.
Ar, Dominic, now!
Dominic, allons !
Well, maybe I'm not a happy lad, so!
Peut-être que je ne suis pas heureux !
Maybe this is the new me!
C'est peut-être le nouveau moi !
Aye.
Oui.
Maybe this is the new me.
C'est peut-être le nouveau moi.
Howdo!
Bonjour !
Jesus Christ, Dominic!
Bon sang, Dominic !
Would you ever stop creeping up on people?
Arrête de surprendre les gens !
You almost gave me a fecking heart attack!
J'aurais pu faire une crise cardiaque !
I wasn't creeping up on ya.
Je ne voulais pas te surprendre.
I was sidling up on ya.
Je voulais me faufiler.
Between you and that ghoul, Jesus!
Toi et cette sorcière, Seigneur !
I always call her a ghoul, too, because she is a ghoul.
Je la traite aussi de sorcière, car c'est ce qu'elle est.
Jeez, we have a lot in common, don't we? Me and you.
On a beaucoup en commun, toi et moi.
Calling old people ghouls and that.
On traite les vieillardes de sorcières et tout ça.
I'm glad I caught you, actually.
Je suis content de te voir.
Because there was somethin' I was wantin' to ask ya, actually.
J'ai quelque chose à te demander.
And discovering how much we have in common,
Et me rendre compte qu'on a tant en commun
well, it just makes me want to ask you even more.
me donne encore plus envie de le faire.
We don't have anything in common.
On n'a rien en commun.
Uh, don't skip ahead.
Pas si vite.
But yeah, what I was wantin' to ask you was...
Mais je voulais te demander...
Somethin' along the lines of...
Quelque chose comme...
Should've planned this, really.
J'aurais dû me préparer.
Well, yeah, what I was wantin' to ask you was...
Je voulais te demander...
You probably wouldn't ever want to, I don't know,
Crois-tu que ça pourrait t'arriver
to fall in love with a boy like me, would ya?
de tomber amoureuse d'un gars comme moi ?
Oh, Dominic, I don't think so, love.
Je ne pense pas, mon chou.
No, yeah, no. Uh, I was thinking no.
Non, je m'en doutais bien.
Not even in the future, like? Like when I'm your age?
Même pas plus tard ? Quand j'aurai ton âge ?
Yeah, no, I didn't think so.
Je m'en doutais bien.
Just thought I'd ask on the off chance, you know,
Je voulais te le demander juste au cas où.
like, "faint heart" and that.
"À cœur vaillant" et tout ça.
Well, there goes that dream.
Tant pis pour ce rêve.
Well,
Bon...
I best go over there and do whatever that thing over there I was gonna do was.
Je devrais aller là-bas et faire le truc que j'allais faire.
Come on, Sammy, you have to dance too.
Allez, Sammy, danse aussi.
How are you, fatty?
Ça va, gros lard ?
Dancing with your dog, is it?
Tu danses avec ton chien ?
Well, who else is gonna dance with ya?
Qui d'autre le ferait ? Ton pauvre chien ne peut pas refuser.
And if you're too rude to be offering me a seat,
Si tu n'as pas la politesse de m'offrir une chaise,
I'll be taking one of me own accord!
je prendrai l'initiative !
Now, how's that for an old hello?
Que dis-tu de ces salutations ?
Have you gone fecking mental?
Es-tu devenu fou ?
Have I gone fecking mental?
Si je suis devenu fou ?
No, I haven't gone fecking mental, actually.
Non, en fait.
Not only have I not gone fecking mental,
Non seulement je ne suis pas fou,
but I have ten fingers to prove I've not gone fecking mental.
mais j'ai dix doigts pour le prouver.
How many fingers do you have to prove you've not gone fecking mental?
Combien de doigts as-tu pour prouver que tu n'es pas fou ?
Nine fingers.
Neuf.
And nine fingers is the epitome of mental.
Neuf doigts, c'est le comble de la folie.
That's right. The epitome!
Tu m'as entendu. Le comble !
Heh. There'll be none of that! I didn't come here for licks!
Arrête ça ! Je ne suis pas venu me faire lécher !
I came here for the opposite of licks.
C'est même tout le contraire.
What's the opposite of licks?
Quel est le contraire de lécher ?
What did you come here for?
Pourquoi es-tu venu ?
I didn't come here for anythin', did I?
Pour rien.
I just came to kick your door in and give you a slagging.
Juste pour enfoncer ta porte et t'insulter.
Well, you've done that, so you can go now.
Tu l'as fait, alors tu peux partir.
Haven't finished yet, have I?
Je n'ai pas fini.
Well, I finished with your door.
Enfin, fini avec ta porte, oui. Pas avec les insultes.
We were doin' so well, Padraic.
Ça allait si bien, Pádraic.
I wasn't doing so well.
Moi, je n'allais pas bien.
I was doing terrible.
J'allais très mal.
All right, I was doin' so well.
D'accord, moi, j'allais si bien.
Yeah, well, it can't all be you, you, you, can it?
Il n'est pas question que de toi.
Yes, it can.
Mais oui.
There's two of us in this. No, there isn't.
- On est deux dans cette histoire. - Non.
It takes two to tango.
Le tango se danse à deux.
I don't want to tango.
Je ne veux pas danser.
Well, you danced with your dog.
Tu dansais avec ton chien.
Talkin' of tangos, how's your new tune comin' along?
En parlant de tango, ça avance, ta chanson ?
Just this morning.
Ce matin même.
No, Colm, that's great, like!
C'est merveilleux, Colm !
That's why I was dancing with me dog.
C'est pour ça que je dansais avec mon chien.
I don't usually dance with me dog.
Je ne fais pas ça d'habitude.
There's no harm dancin' with your dog.
Il n'y a rien de mal à ça.
I'd dance with me donkey if I knew how. And she did.
Je danserais avec mon âne si on savait comment.
Is it good?
Elle est bonne ?
Your tune?
Ta chanson ?
Mm, what's it called?
Quel en est le titre ?
"The Banshees of Inisherin," I was thinking.
J'ai pensé à "Les banshees d'Inisherin".
But there are no banshees on Inisherin.
Il n'y a pas de banshees à Inisherin.
I know, I just like the double S-H sounds.
Je sais, mais j'aime le son "sh".
Aye.
Oui.
There's plenty of double S-H on Inisherin.
Il y a pas mal de sons "sh" à Inisherin.
Maybe there are banshees, too.
Il y a peut-être même des banshees.
I just don't think that they scream to portend death anymore.
Sauf qu'elles ne crient plus pour présager la mort, selon moi.
I think they just sit back, amused, and observe.
Elles s'assoient et observent d'un air amusé.
Portend?
Présager ?
Yeah.
Oui.
I keep having thoughts about playing it for you at your funeral.
Je me dis que je pourrais la jouer à tes funérailles.
But that wouldn't be fair on either of us, would it?
Mais ce serait injuste pour nous deux, pas vrai ?
Well, that's great that you finished your tune, Colm.
C'est merveilleux que tu aies fini ta chanson.
That's more than great.
Plus que merveilleux.
really great.
Vraiment merveilleux.
We could celebrate your tune, like.
On pourrait fêter ta chanson.
Only if you'd like, like.
Seulement si tu en as envie.
But I could run up ahead. Order them in.
Mais je pourrais aller commander d'avance.
Why don't you do that, Padraic?
Fais donc ça, Pádraic.
Why don't I run up...
Je vais aller
and order them?
commander d'avance.
Well, I will so.
Je vais faire ça.
Jeez, that went well! And maybe on the way,
Ça s'est bien passé ! Peut-être qu'en route,
I can find that student friend of yours, that Declan fella!
je verrai ton ami étudiant, Declan !
I told him his daddy was dying, so he'd feck off home
Je lui ai dit que son père était mourant
and leave us alone, but there's no need now!
pour qu'il nous laisse tranquilles, mais c'est inutile !
Sure he could join us.
Il pourrait se joindre à nous.
What are you sitting over there for when I'm over here?
Que fais-tu assis là alors que je suis ici ?
Just thought I'd have a sit for meself, you know.
J'avais envie de m'asseoir tout seul.
Wait for me friend.
J'attends mon ami.
Are you fecking joking me?
Tu plaisantes ?
Your four-fingered friend?
Ton ami à quatre doigts ?
I mean, are you fecking joking me?
Tu plaisantes ou quoi ?
No, I'm not fecking joking ya.
Pas du tout.
He just needed a bit of tough love was all.
Il fallait juste être ferme avec lui.
Siobhan, do you want a sherry?
Un sherry, Siobhán ?
No.Righty-ho.
- Non. - Très bien.
What are you doin'?
Que fais-tu ?
Me? Yes, you.
- Moi ? - Oui, toi.
Nothing. Just drinkin'.
Rien. Je bois.
Not waitin'?Not waitin'.
- Tu n'attends pas ? - Non.
Well, he is waitin', Siobhan. He's waitin' for Colm Doherty.
Mais oui, il attend Colm Doherty.
I amn't waitin'.
Je n'attends pas.
He just told me he was waitin'.
Il vient de me dire qu'il attendait.
Telltale!
Rapporteur !
Come home with me, Padraic. I've somethin' to discuss with ya.
Rentrons, Pádraic. Je dois te parler de quelque chose.
You've somethin' to discuss with me?
Me parler de quelque chose ?
That sounds, uh...
Ça me semble...
I don't want to discuss somethin'.
Je ne veux parler de rien.
Well, ya have to, 'cause I'm leavin'.
Il le faut, car je vais partir.
Leavin'?
Partir ?
Like leavin'?
Partir pour vrai ?
Like...
Dans le sens de...
not staying?
Pas rester ?
Yeah.
Oui.
But what about me?
Et moi, alors ?
What about you?
Quoi, toi ?
I'll have no friends at all left!
Je n'ai plus d'amis !
You'll have Dominic. Ah here!
- Tu as Dominic. - Allons !
And he's gone off me now, too.
Il ne m'aime plus non plus.
What kind of a place is it when the village gom goes off ya?
Tu parles d'un endroit, même l'idiot du village ne m'aime plus !
And who's gonna do the cookin'?
Qui va cuisiner ?
Oh, that's your first question, isn't it? "Who's gonna do the cookin'?"
C'est ta première question ? "Qui va cuisiner ?"
Well, it wasn't me first question, was it?
Non, ma première question était : "Et moi, alors ?"
Padraic.
Pádraic.
Padraic!
Pádraic !
Now? But you can't be leavin' now!
Maintenant ? Tu ne peux pas partir maintenant !
I can be leavin' now.
Je peux partir maintenant.
I can't be waitin' round for any more of this madness!
Je ne peux pas rester pour ces sottises !
What the hell did you say to him, Padraic?
Que lui as-tu dit, Pádraic ?
Nothin' really.
Rien.
Well, I'd sort of had a chat with Dominic earlier.
J'ai parlé à Dominic un peu plus tôt.
And a new sort of,
Et on disait
you know, standin' up for meself sort of tack we thought I should try.
que je devrais essayer de m'affirmer davantage.
God!
Seigneur !
It was all going fine until he chopped off all his fingers.
Tout allait bien jusqu'à ce qu'il se coupe les doigts.
Me books wouldn't fit.
Je manque de place pour mes livres.
Would you look after them for me?
Peux-tu les garder pour moi ?
Ar, don't go, Siobhan.
Ne pars pas, Siobhán.
They're all I have, really.
C'est tout ce que j'ai.
Apart from the obvious.
À part toi, évidemment.
You'll be back soon, won't you, Siobhan?
Reviendras-tu bientôt, Siobhán ?
Don't say, "Oh, Padraic."
Ne dis pas : "Oh, Pádraic."
Say yes.
Dis oui.
Ah, Jenny.
Jenny.
Oh.
Oh !
I don't want to talk.
Je ne veux pas parler.
Don't go killin' his dog now.
Ne tue pas son chien.
And don't be puttin' things in me head
Ne me mettez pas d'idées dans la tête
that weren't there in the first feckin' place,
qui n'étaient pas là avant,
you feckin' nutbag!
espèce de cinglée !
What would I ever hurt you for?
Pourquoi te ferais-je du mal ?
You're the only nice thing about him.
Tu es ce qu'il y a de mieux chez lui.
How are you, Padraic? You're lookin' well.
Ça va, Pádraic ? Tu as l'air en forme.
I don't need your apologies, all right?
Je n'ai pas besoin de tes excuses.
It's a relief to me.
C'est un soulagement pour moi.
So, let's just call it quits
Convenons que c'est terminé
and agree to go our separate ways, for good this time.
et qu'on ira chacun de son côté, pour de bon.
Your fat fingers killed me little donkey today.
Tes gros doigts ont tué mon petit âne.
So, no, we won't call it quits.
Alors non, ce n'est pas terminé.
We'll call it the start.
Ce n'est que le début.
You're jokin' me.Yeah, no.
- Tu plaisantes. - Non.
I'm not jokin' ya.
Je ne plaisante pas.
So tomorrow, Sunday,
Demain, dimanche,
God's day, around 2:00,
jour du Seigneur, vers 14 h,
I'm going to call up to your house and I'm gonna set fire to it,
j'irai chez toi pour y mettre le feu,
and hopefully you'll still be inside it.
et j'espère que tu seras dans la maison.
But I won't be checkin' either way.
Je ne vérifierai pas.
Just be sure and leave your dog outside.
Assure-toi de laisser ton chien dehors.
I've nothing against that gom.
Je n'ai rien contre ce bêta.
Or you can do whatever's in your power to stop me.
Tu peux faire ce que tu veux pour m'arrêter.
To our graves we're taking this.
C'est parti, jusqu'à la mort.
To one of our graves, anyways.
Pour un de nous, du moins.
Here.
Te voilà.
I've a bone to pick with you, dreary.
On a des comptes à régler.
Is that little gobshite of mine at your place again?
Mon petit merdeux est-il encore chez toi ?
Leave him, Peadar. His donkey's just died.
Laisse-le, Peadar. Son âne est mort.
Did he?
Ah bon ?
The little miniature fella?
Le petit âne miniature ?
Well, Jesus, boys, I'll tell ya this much...
Seigneur, vous deux, je vais vous dire...
Two o'clock.
Quatorze heures.
I killed a miniature donkey.
J'ai tué un âne miniature.
It was by accident...
C'était un accident,
but I do feel bad about it.
mais je me sens mal.
Do you think God gives a damn about miniature donkeys, Colm?
Croyez-vous que Dieu se soucie des ânes miniatures, Colm ?
I fear he doesn't.
Je crains que non.
And I fear that's where it's all gone wrong.
Je crains que ce soit là le problème.
Is that it?
C'est tout ?
Is what it?
Quoi ?
Aren't you forgetting a couple of things?
N'oubliez-vous pas quelques choses ?
No, I think I've covered it.
Non, j'ai tout dit.
Ah here.
Ah, ça.
If punching a policeman is a sin,
Si frapper un policier est un péché,
we may as well just pack up and go home.
autant renoncer à tout ceci et rentrer chez nous.
And self-mutilation is a sin.
L'automutilation est aussi un péché.
It's one of the biggest.
L'un des plus graves.
Is it?
Ah bon ?
Self-mutilation, so you have me there.
Automutilation, vous me tenez.
Multiplied by five.
Multipliée par cinq.
How's the despair?
Et le désespoir ?
It's back a bit.
Il est revenu un peu.
But you're not gonna do anything about it?
Mais vous ne comptez rien y faire ?
I'm not gonna do anything about it, no.
Je ne compte rien y faire, non.
Dear Padraic,
Cher Pádraic,
There's a river running past my window as I write,
Je vois couler une rivière de ma fenêtre,
and the people already seem less bitter and mental.
et les gens semblent moins amers et cinglés.
I'm not sure why, but I think it's 'cause a lot of them are from Spain.
C'est peut-être parce que beaucoup viennent d'Espagne.
Mostly, I wanted to say there's a spare bed here for you, Padraic.
Je voulais surtout te dire qu'il y a un lit de libre pour toi.
And with the war almost over, I think there'd be work for ya here.
Avec la guerre qui achève, tu trouverais du travail ici.
Because there's nothing for you on Inisherin.
Il n'y a rien pour toi à Inisherin.
Nothing but more bleakness and grudges
Rien que de la misère et de la rancune,
and loneliness and spite
de la solitude et du mépris,
and the slow passing of time until death.
et le temps qui s'étiole jusqu'à la mort.
And sure, you can do that anywhere.
Tout ça se trouve n'importe où.
So come, Padraic. Leave there.
Alors viens, Pádraic. Quitte cet endroit.
Dominic can look after Jenny and the rest of your animals.
Dominic s'occupera de Jenny et des autres animaux.
They could move into the house together.
Ils pourraient tous habiter la maison.
So come now, Padraic, please.
Viens maintenant, je t'en prie.
Before it's all too late.
Avant qu'il soit trop tard.
Dear Siobhan.
Chère Siobhán,
Obviously, I don't know what "ensconced" is,
j'ignore ce que veut dire "incruster",
but I thank you for the offer of the free bed and the whatnot.
mais merci de m'offrir un lit et tout le reste.
But I won't be takin' you up on it, I'm afraid.
J'ai bien peur de devoir refuser.
As I told you, me life is on Inisherin.
Je te l'ai dit, ma vie est à Inisherin.
Me friends, me animals.
Mes amis, mes animaux.
Even now as I write,
Pendant que je t'écris,
little donkey Jenny is looking at me, saying,
mon petit âne me regarde comme pour dire :
"Please don't go, Padraic. We'd miss ya."
"Ne pars pas, Pádraic. Tu nous manquerais."
And nuzzling me, the gilly-gooly.
Il se blottit contre moi, le nigaud.
Get off, Jenny.
Éloigne-toi, Jenny.
In other news,
Autres nouvelles...
in sadder news, actually,
Des nouvelles tristes, en fait.
I won't be able to ask Dominic anything, I'm afraid.
Je ne pourrai rien demander à Dominic.
Because they found him in the lake this morning.
On l'a repêché du lac ce matin.
I suppose he must've slipped and fell in.
Il a dû glisser et tomber à l'eau.
So, there'd be no one to take care of the animals, anyway.
Il n'y a donc personne pour s'occuper des animaux.
No other news, really.
Je n'ai rien d'autre à dire.
Except that I love you, Siobhan.
Sauf que je t'aime, Siobhán.
And I miss ya.
Et que tu me manques.
And I hope I'll see ya again someday.
J'espère qu'on se reverra un jour.
If you ever come back home.
Si tu reviens à la maison.
Come back home, Siobhan.
Reviens à la maison, Siobhán.
Yours sincerely, your loving brother...
Meilleures salutations de ton frère qui t'aime,
Padraic Suilleabhain.
Pádraic Súilleabháin.
Suppose me house makes us quits.
Avec ma maison, j'imagine qu'on est quittes.
If you'd stayed in your house, that would've made us quits.
Si tu étais resté à l'intérieur, on serait quittes.
But you didn't, did ya, so it doesn't, does it?
Mais tu es sorti, alors on ne l'est pas.
I'm sorry about your donkey, Padraic.
Je suis désolé pour ton âne, Pádraic.
Honestly, I am.
Sincèrement.
I don't fucking care.
Je m'en fiche.
Haven't heard any rifle fire from the mainland in a day or two.
Je n'ai pas entendu de tirs sur la grande île depuis un jour ou deux.
I think they're coming to the end of it.
Je crois qu'ils en ont presque fini.
I'm sure they'll be at it again soon enough, aren't you?
Ils recommenceront sûrement bientôt, tu ne crois pas ?
Some things there's no movin' on from.
Certaines choses ne se pardonnent pas.
And I think that's a good thing.
Je crois que c'est bien comme ça.
Padraic.
Pádraic.
Thanks for lookin' after me dog for me, anyways.
Merci d'avoir veillé sur mon chien.
Any time.
Il n'y a pas de quoi.